Guide to the Meyer London Papers TAM.028
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Meyer London Papers
1910-1959
TAM.028
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
2.5 linear feet (6 boxes)
Meyer London (1871-1926) was a Socialist, labor lawyer and the first Socialist ever elected to the United States House of Representatives, representing New York City's Lower East Side (1915-1917, 1919-1921). The papers contain correspondence, speeches, handbills, press clippings, scrapbooks of London's congressional speeches, and photographs, chiefly relating to his political career. There are also materials relating to the Meyer London Memorial Committee, the dedication of the Meyer London public school (P.S. 2) on the Lower East Side of New York, and a personal tribute by Lena Morrow Lewis.
London, Meyer, 1871-1926
Box 1-5
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: I, Papers (arranged alphabetically); II, Fragile Originals.
Historical/Biographical Note
Meyer London (1871-1926) was a Socialist, a labor lawyer (a graduate of New York University Law School, and later the counsel for the International Ladies' Garment Workers Union), and as a Socialist Party candidate, was elected to the United States House of Representatives, representing New York City's Lower East Side, serving two terms, 1916-1918 and 1920-1922. As a Congressman, he opposed U.S. entry into World War I, and introduced numerous labor legislation bills. Upon his death, the library of the Rand School of Social Science (1906-1956), a workers' school in New York City, associated with the Socialist Party, named its library the Meyer London Memorial Library, and in in 1959 an elementary school on the Lower East Side was named in his honor (the Meyer London Public School, also known as P.S. 2).
Scope and Contents note
The papers contain correspondence, speeches, handbills, press clippings, scrapbooks of London's Congressional speeches and resolutions introduced, and photographs, chiefly relating to his political career. Most of the correspondence to London relates to bills he introduced or positions he took, such as his 1916 call for Federal unemployment insurance. Includes correspondence relating to Socialist Party affairs; speeches concerning World War I neutrality and amnesty and Puerto Rican rights; Records of the Meyer London Memorial Committee, relating to the dedication of the Meyer London public school (P.S. 2) on the Lower East Side of New York; messages of condolence to Mrs. London; and a personal tribute of Lena Morrow Lewis.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Transfered from the Rand School Archives in 1963. There is no earlier provenance information. The accession number 1960.003 is associated with this collection.
Lewis, Lena Morrow; London, Meyer, 1871-1926; London, Meyer, 1871-1926 -- Death and burial; Meyer London Memorial Committee.; Meyer London Public School.; Correspondence.; Jewish socialists |z United States.; Legislators |z United States.; Socialists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Socialists |z United States.; Speeches.; Unemployment insurance |z United States.; World War, 1914-1918 |z United States.
- American Association for Labor Legislation: Letter to M.L., re: Health Insurance Legislation, Jan 4, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Citizens' Mass Meeting-Protest Against Closing the Brooklyn Navy Yard, March 10, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Clippings-English, Italian, 1916-1922 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clippings: Yiddish, 1916-n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Clippings: Yiddish, 1957, 1958, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Cloak and Shirt Makers Union: Letters to Meyer London, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Congressional Calendar, Oct 27, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence: Congressional, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Congressional Record- Excerpts Including Statements by Meyer London, 1916-1918, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence: Congressional, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence-Congressional, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence- Congressional, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence-Congressional, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence-Congressional, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence-Family, 1915, 1917, 1921, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence- General, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 15A)
- East Side Agitation Committee, Socialist Party: Peace Resolution, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Election- Affidavits Regarding Voting Day Irregularities on Nov 5, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Election-Campaign Materials, 1919, 1920, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Gompers, Samuel: Letter Inviting M.L. to Meeting at White House on Cost of Living, Jun 9, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Intercollegiate Socialist Society: City College of N.Y. Chapter: Letter to Meyer London, Jun 25, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Journal- Meyer London Congressman Elect, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Justice, Jewish Edition- Yiddish, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- London, Isabel, M (M.D.): Meyer London: An Appreciation, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- London, Meyer: Death Clippings, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- London, Meyer: Letter to S.L.P. Poale Zion of America, Sep 6, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "Meyer London": (Anonymous Biographical ts; 7pp) (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Meyer London Memorial Committee 10th Anniversary, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Meyer London Memorial Clippings (in Yiddish): 25th Anniversary, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Meyer London Memorial Committee Correspondence: Other Documents, 1950-1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Meyer London Memorial Committee- 25th Anniversary, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Meyer London Memorial Library, 1949, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Meyer London School (P.S. 2, Manhattan, N.Y.): Campaign For, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Meyer London School (P.S. 2, Manhattan, N.Y.)-Dedication, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Meyer London Handwritten Notes on Russian Debt, Visti of Admiral Kolchack to U.S., Jun 27, 1918; Jul 18, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- New York Call: Telegrams to Meyer London re: Leon Trotsky's Seizure and Internment by British Authorities, April 1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Photographs- Meyer London and Others, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Reapportionment of Meyer London's Congressional District, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Socialist Party: officials and Members' Letters to Meyer London( incl. Frank Bohr, Julius Gerber, Seymour Stedman, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Socialist Committee on Information (Washington D.C.): Resolutions and Meyer London Speech on Child Labor Law, 1918, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Speech: Labor Day, Sep 2, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Speech: The National Government and Unemployment, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Speech: Socialist Party National Congress, May, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Speech: (Yiddish), Dec 6, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Speeches and Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Tariff Bills, 1913, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Unemployment and Social Insurance, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Workman's Circle Cemetary Dept. Letter to Meyer London, May 3, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- United States Congress House of Representatives: Speeches and Resolutions, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- U.S. Congress House of Representatives: Speeches and Resolutions, Dec, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- U.S. Congress House of Representatives: Speeches and Resolutions, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- U.S. Congress House of Representatives (64th-65th Congress) Speeches and Resolutions, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- U.S. Congress House of Representatives: Speeches and Resolutions, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- U.S. Congress House of Representatives: Speeches and Resolutions, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- U.S. Congress House of Representatives (64th Congress, 2nd Session-65th Congress, 2nd Session): Speeches and Resolutions (Scrapbook), 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- U.S. Congress House of Representatives (64th Congress, 2nd Session- 65th Congress, 2nd Session part II): Speeches and Resolutions (Scrapbook), 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- U.S. Congress. House of Representatives (67th Congress, 1st Session) Speeches and Resolutions (Scrapbook), 1921 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- U.S. Congress. House of Representatives (67th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions) Speeches and Resolutions (Scrapbook), 1921-1922 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- U.S. Congress. House of Representatives (67th Congress, 3rd and 4th Sessions) Speeches and Resolutions (Scrapbook), 1922-1923 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folders 1-8, c. 1916-c. 1964 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folder 8, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folder 8, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folders 8-12, c. 1915-c. 1921 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folders 12-14, c. 1917-c. 1922 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folder 14, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folders 14-15, c. 1915-c. 1926 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folder 15, c. 1915-c. 1926 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folder 15, c. 1915-c. 1926 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folder 15, c. 1915-c. 1926 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folders 15-17, c. 1912-c. 1962 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folder 17, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folders 21-25, c. 1916-c. 1954 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folders 1-3, c. 1936-c. 1954 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folders 3-4, c. 1950-c. 1954 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 6, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 7, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folders 7-12, c. 1917-c. 1959 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folders 12-14, c. 1917-c. 1918 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folders 15-18, c. 1910-c. 1918 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 18, Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folders 18-21, 1912-1913 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folders 1-3, 1915-1916 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folders 3-4, 1916-1917 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folders 4-6, c. 1917-c. 1921 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 7, c. 1917-c. 1918 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 8, c. 1917-c. 1918 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 9, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 11, c. 1922-c. 1923 (Box 6, Folder 4)